Let's see what this sounds like, nope that didn't sound good, alright why is it sounding
messy here, ok cool so these are not in time, cool maybe these don't, I think it just gets
a bit messy here, just looking for that ring, you can just see it there, just my ears just
picked that up then, oh that's better, right I'm still not convinced with the pin to funk
hi-hats but let's keep them in there for now, I'm going to clean this up, I'm going to save
it quickly, let's try and improve this snare now.
So if you remember I made one of the white noises quite short, oops don't know what I've
was just listening to there is the tail with the white noise and all of a sudden it had
this kind of resonance in there, gave me an idea, wondering if I could like add a ding to
the snare, there's a couple of ways we can do that, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to duplicate the sine wave, let's dump this at the bottom and I'm just going to literally
add a ring, so our fundamental is C, that's where the snare is hitting, so if we do, so
that's C, so C sharp D, D sharp E F, so that's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, if we go plus 5 and 2 down that
should be an F, let's confirm that with an EQ, it's quite high though, that is an F, how
does that sound? Let's put a little, I'm going to remove this, actually I'll keep that on, this
is the pitch envelope by the way, master tune, I'm going to take this, I want to...
it's a bit too much distortion on this I think, so let's ease up on that, cool, this might be better,
doesn't sound great, but let's hear it in the mix, nope I do not like that at all, okay let's try
another example, I have, what we can do is let's try some frequency shifting,
try something like this,
sounds weird,
okay that doesn't sound great,
right let's try some convolution reverb,
oh thank you pardon,
so if you go to my Facebook page I did a session on how I go about making my convolution reverb
impulses, convolution reverb is a very cool tool because it allows you to actually load in your
impulses, so what I do is I make a sine wave and add white noise to it and as you can see here I've
made an impulse for every single note on the scale, so why isn't it working?
strange, hold on let's see if I can get this to work,
the reason it's not working I think was because it was on the wrong channel, brilliant
here we go, right so as you can hear
there's a huge difference in sound, so I can choose all my impulses, these impulses are tuned,
so if I wanted F like I was trying before, maybe a higher one, how does that sound?
okay it's sounding a bit over the top,
kind of like that, let's try a G sharp four,
this is kind of cool,
so with convolution reverb if I
currently got this set to about 17% it was
and this audio file is very long, the tail is also very long, like I've got the length
set to a very short amount if I leave this open
it's very long, right so I always find it very difficult to
I always find it very difficult to control that the envelope
so what I want to do first I want to make sure I'm happy with the actual impulse I've selected
and then I'm just going to record this in 100% wet and then mix it in with the original one,
so the first thing I want to do is make sure I've got the right impulse,
it's kind of like in G sharp four
maybe a G
let's just listen to that in context for a sec
I think the G sharp is going to be a little bit confusing musically, a bit too much going on
probably so let's just go cool let's roll with an F for now and then I'm going to leave this impulse on
and then every time I kind of change the melody I can also tune this convolution
basically to that section which is amazing so I'm going to quickly make a new audio file set
that to resample record I just want to make sure I've got nothing else armed yeah that's good
right let's record this in
oh I'm recording everything I want to solo this let's go
I also want this set to 100% wet otherwise it completely defeats the purpose
third time lucky guys
good
all right so now I've got a little bit more control with
a little bit more control of my envelopes now
sorry my google drive keeps giving me warnings thanks
cool right now I could take a bit low end out of this
I think that might be good enough let's listen
right I'll take this off what a difference
yeah so I literally use this technique on a lot of my snares and a lot of people ask me
how do you get that kind of ringy sound that's how you get it
all right let's check this out shall we
it could be a bit longer I think
cool right next job let's copy these things over
yeah lovely
so I want to get all my hi hats I've got nothing
nothing muted now I'm using all of these so let's roll with this duplicate duplicate duplicate
all right there's something weird going on the hi hats here
I think
I think this bass could be improved loads as well
so I just listened to that section and my thought process was wow that sounds terrible
why does it sound terrible first thought was okay maybe something to do with those hi hats
but I think a lot more productive approach is to fix this bass first
so
could be definitely a lot louder
so that master tune
how does this sound actually
I might just leave a hole in there in the bass because the kick's there
so
cool let's try and improve this first and then we can figure that out later
sounds very far behind and flat
let's try and push it a bit harder I think so I'm going to use tube driver
that might be better
I'm going to take a bit of this mid out
so
let's roll it out and see what we get to
so I maybe want to try and leave a bit of space between
this section let's see what this sounds like
maybe we could make this section longer as well
okay so
maybe let's try and get some more of our existing bass sounds in might replace this sound
let's drop a few of these in
what did this sound like
not sure that's gonna fit but
could work
G sharp C okay the B is out of scale so if we try E
so
kind of works
I'm going to leave that there for now I can improve it
or we can use it somewhere else let's just throw it in randomly and see
what's going on with this audio file actually it's a weird position
okay something weird just went on there
okay cool quite like this last one the first one is a bit
this sounds a bit like carnivore something
I like that at the end that's cool
not bad let's see how this sounds here
could work actually
let's give it a go
maybe let's just remove this one
okay not sure about that we'll keep it in there has some potential for the pre-drop sound
that also has potential for somewhere oops
okay
what note was this D sharp let's go with E
nope right let's get rid of those we tried okay number eight
so we're still sketching still sketching trying to find the breakthrough
interesting
oh
love that ending isn't that the same that
nope cool now why does that sound good like it's meant to be
the reason why is because our fundamental is a G
root note is E we put the root note E which is in scale F harmonic minor
but I think I think I know from doing this quite a lot that that harmonic you're hearing
that harmonic you're hearing is a G
and let's have a look
okay there's a little
okay
quite complex
what's seven doing
okay that doesn't sound great
I think I'll keep it
keep it as it was right cool so we are making progress
only thing I'm really still disliking is this bar here so there's a couple of things we can do
continue working on this sound for a while or we could move on and then build out the tune
now I'm the type of person that would like to sit on this loop for a little longer
so I'm going to spend an hour offline to see if I can improve this
try and improve this section I'm gonna spend an hour going through my old samples to see if
I can find something that jumps out ideally I want something percussive like the dun-dun-dun-dun-dun
because this is very very long moving and I like to compliment that with a percussive
something percussive after it cool so I'll be back to you and I'll see where we've got from there
right I think I've got something a bit better than we had
literally didn't tell me long just went through my presets I've got a big selection of presets I've
saved here over the last couple of weeks and literally I just kept the same setting so previously
we had the stabby ones and I literally duplicated it and clicked the third preset I came across
and I was like okay that works a lot better so there's a lot more detail in the stereo field
as well so you can definitely utilize that
cool so I'm going to get rid of this old one one thing I want to do is try and energize this up
a bit I want to try and utilize some ghost snares I think maybe we could already use the existing snare
let's see
kind of cool I'm gonna see if I can use another another snare in that place
um we already have some shuffles in here that it's really important not to actually that one's muted
let's see
okay
just think that slows it down a bit and we're gonna on the next bar we're gonna jump into something new
I'm gonna keep this like like this for now
let's duplicate this setting actually what I'm gonna do is I'm going to group these
what I hear in my head is a kind of synth over the top of this I mean literally this is just
drums and bass which is fine but I want to try and spice up a bit so I'm gonna duplicate my bass patch
I try something like this
I don't want the initial hit though
cool so let's use a different filter instead and try and see if we can get
something cool going with that
I'm gonna put this one really wide
now I listen to it in context I'm not sure it's going to work
it's not sounding amazing let's take the guitar off
let's go a bit higher up on the
cool let's add a wavetable
could be cool could be cool let's let's remove these and cut some low end out to see what it sounds like
let's mix it in
gives it a bit more detail I'm not happy with that yet but
it just makes it it makes it more interesting to my ears I'm not happy with the I'm going to come
back to that I just want to see how this flows now I was also going to add this go snare here
so let's do that as well I'm just going to go through my snares and see
if we have a little that might work
a little go snare
so I've obviously got my kick here and I don't want the overlapping
not sure sounds a bit messy
let's try something like that
my gapatune
better let's remove this what's going on here messy messy
I'm going to ease back on these the more I listen to them
the more I do not like them and that's okay let's try something else
so again these are literally snares that I've collected for years that I've made in tunes
I've made in previous sessions like I showed you before
and once I'm short
could work
let's give it a go
not bad
yeah kind of like that very short which is great
let's see if we can repeat it here this might not work but worth a go
hmm
sounds very robotic to me when you start using go snares like this
I just want to isolate these drums
let's see
let's clean up these low ends
I think it is those high
something weird going on here
better better
when you're using a few layers you know you always got a check to make sure nothing's clashing
I think I've screwed up here somehow as well and let me copy these over again
I guess the same is for these ones yep
okay cool let's go with these
better
cool let's listen to the bass with the bass
right those things are annoying me a bit now
they have something kind of cool about
going to take the low end out and stuff
so
it's going to make this last one a bit shorter
once I've gone that last snare now and I think after that we'll be able to build this tune out
let's try something like this just on the last
not bad
it's not bad what I want to try and do now is I want to do two things I want to add some kind
of effects to it reverse small reverse sounds just to liven up and try and give the impression
to the listener that something's going to happen and secondly I want to try and mix these
basses a bit better so I've got a feeling if I solo the sidechain which at the moment is just the
basses all these basses are going to sound very different let's give it a listen
yes they do lots of clicks as well from the sidechain which we will fix later
especially on that one so let's try and get these bass sounds sounding like they're working together
so
it's the first one I am going to make this a lot shorter so it's visually a bit easier
yeah
I miss some some sub here
right so I try two little things then as you could as you could hear the sound change drastically
first I was I was thinking I could just put a sine wave under the sub
and then I just wanted to see how this reacted
so I just put a boost up on the fundamental but the problem is because it's pre distortion
because the EQ is before the distortion the distortion is changing its reaction to the
harmonics being fed into it so if you we just bump up the bass all those harmonics now are
tamed because the large the the sound with the most most energy that's being sent into
distortion is now the fundamental it was anyway but it's on a stream scale
so the harmonic distribution of the distortion is going to change immensely so an easy way to
fix it is do some post
so you can see here sub gets completely lost I don't like doing this but
may work
let's think what's the solution I'm gonna try and group these and put a sub under it I don't
think this is gonna work and the reason I don't think it's gonna work is because the
because the saw waves are detuned as we mentioned and talked about before it starts
phasing and creating that kind of cool LFO sound so if I feed a sine wave which is not detuned it's
going to completely completely destroy that movement but I'm wondering if I put it through
a different distortion instead of guitaric you can hear that's quite a clean tone now
I can take the erosion off
let's see how far we can let's see how loud we can make this something like that might do the ticket
sounding a bit better
more sub definitely
I'm gonna mute this a second that release it's so annoying
much better
cool that sounding good I could even turn this down a bit maybe
oh we could take the low end out let's just see what this sounds like
okay now we're talking
okay that's a big improvement
right so now we're engineering
we are engineering a hundred percent
let's turn these on
right let's go for this one now
let's get this looped see if we can improve this
sound
we can definitely improve this sound
that was cool more wide
if I do the same technique as before put a sub under it like that
much better
I just want to quickly check how stereo my drums are
so what I'm doing now is I'm adding obviously lots of stereo interest to this bass
and I want to create a mental image of my head of what's happening in the stereo image
so I'm just going to quickly use my utility for this
um you set this to mid-side
so there's quite a bit going on there
that's my mono signal obviously
it's okay yeah lots of high-end interest
so I just wanted to avoid any kind of clashing there
let's go back and un-solo this
cool so let's get some
let's get some sub under this I'm going to do exactly the same way as I did before I think so
grouped this my utility was just turning it down because it had that really annoying release
on it um let's duplicate this
let's take this mono as well I can also take this this off as well
what's making it sound like here we go why is there a click on it
I think that's the side chain let's have a listen
nope
that sounds nice to me
it's kind of funny because I don't typically do this
as in layering a sub under it I always try and use one patch but for some reason it's
sounding pretty okay to me so far this this technique
the only thing that's really annoying me is the clicks at the moment so I have to
find a solution for that let's check this out in the mix
cool that's sounding way better
cool cool cool um so I still need to fix the clicks but I don't want to get into that now
it might be a workflow killer
let's see what's going on here very cool sound actually
what's going on with this sub sounds very weak
again lots of clicks very frustrating
let's check this
interesting I think I had it on off
and that already sounds much better let's check that out
that's sounding good to me what's this vocoder doing
hmm it's definitely adding something
I want to get this a bit louder I think
can we just turn it up let's see
okay so one thing I'm noticing is this this base is really wide and then this one kind of
is somewhere in the middle and there's not really a kind of
connection between them like literally sounds like two baselines and in some instances that
can sound cool but I'm wondering if we can kind of gel them together somehow
let's isolate these
okay already they're they're working much much much better than they were before
so it's good to make that progress
so I'm constantly questioning what I'm doing constantly
constantly trying to make improvements
what else is going on here
okay
that chorus effect is quite cool remember us doing that
um yeah I like that let's see if it glued together with this one a bit more
sounds even wider that could also be an option where it starts
nice and it would make sense because next is that
next bit one thing I definitely want to fix is this overlapping into the next bar
it's very messy at the moment so I still need to fix those clicks
it's there an erosion on this what's making
high end sounds
sounds very wet let's see how this sounds like
sounds
cool not bad okay cool let's see how this flows into the next section
right the first thing that jumps out to me and it probably also jumps out to you is that
arp is terrible
literally just comes out of nowhere like a bit carnival isn't it so let's see if we can improve that
I think instead of it starting untuned and finishing detuned we want to change that around
so it starts off very detuned and a bit and then it slowly tunes goes back into tune so
let's see where do we do that again chorus swell LFO 2
LFO 2
where was is it chorus swell
LFO 3
let me just loop this for a bit
LFO 4
all that could work
no it can't
LFO 5
I wonder if I can use this Reese thing high drone the first
okay no
LFO 5
all right so this section I'm fairly pleased with at the moment all kind of it sounds like one tune
but this section is not sounding amazing yet
so many clicks can we fix that
cool works much better so I'm just smoothing out the the function on the LFO tool definitely
helps you remove the clicks
how can we improve this now
is there like a low pass on this or something I should remember I only made this yesterday
here we go
LFO 5
better
still want a bit more movement in there though so let's try
um let's try a notch
LFO 5
let's try a band 12
cool that could work
LFO 5
a bit more movement
all right let's check out this one now
so the sub gets a bit lost compared compared to the others let's have a look
I think it's just the distortion to be honest so much distortion
better
I wonder if we can get this any louder as well
let's go
I'm going to change the kick as well
use the low one but not sure
now right let's dump the F kick
it was a good idea but
right definitely an improvement
now what I'm going to do is look through some effects I want to see if I can
I want to see if I can improve this somehow
so when I mean my effects I mean like little reverse things like
something like that
so we're tuning I normally do this by ear
sounds a bit spaceship to me
okay that could work
definitely doesn't need it that
it's very quiet
let's give these a go should we
maybe this works on that last one
but too much it's gonna randomly shorten it
not big fan
this is from an unfinished tune I did
nothing great in there
okay cool
okay shouldn't be turning this up plus six
and although the sample is quite soft but I think I need to do a review of the level soon
maybe that goes before the drop
I'm still not happy with this up yet
I think I'm gonna leave it like that for now
like come in handy
cool that's very intense like that
it's down on that a bit I just want to make a little fade in here I don't want to
I don't want to have this rammed I mean look at this waveform it's already blown up and
after it there's going to come a huge amount of energy so
I think we can improve the the punch
but that'll come with our mix now so we can think about that later
some way to get this kick a bit more
just double check my sidechain a sec
maybe I don't need a really long sidechain well we're gonna cover this in a minute
right so we are making progress the drop is already sounding okay
I'm kind of liking how the build-up sounds as well so far the really intense this section
that's sounding very great cool and it's definitely working already
that bit's working already the only bit I'm disliking now is this section
this last bit's cool
but this bass is still not great so let's see if we can improve that
I think this is very mono as well so maybe we can in keeping with the rest of the bass sounds we can
join
interesting
oh that sounds cool so um I just put the hype dimension on serum and I've left the mix up
so it's almost phasing
I like that it sounds almost like pan to the left and right but it's giving a very
unique effect and if you notice my sub is directly being sent out so that's mono
unfazed
yeah it's a bit sounds a bit panned
such a huge difference
so
where was this low pass
so I'm just going to AB this definitely an improvement definitely sounds interesting I'm
not sure it's the final thing yet
the unison is very weird maybe let's pick a three instead
yeah number two unison works
I think
oh that could be quite cool as well let's see if we can put this just on the last bar
so
not bad definitely sounds more interesting I'm not sure I'm like yes that's the one but
I think in some respects what you have to do is look at the sound objectively and think okay
does it sound more interesting does it fit the tune more does it fit with the rest of
sounds that are around it and I think it does tickle those boxes what I just said
cool oh wow that release really annoys me
I think what we might do is bring that up in layer for a whole section rather than just have
it for two bars
oh yeah cool that was my
I'm gonna turn this up a bit
let's also
try something cool with this
there is a cool plugin and I've never used this plugin so we can do it together
it's a granular synth or granular tool from max for life
so
granulator I think it's called there we go granulator two okay let me make a quick
oh
cool all right let me just drop granular here
faster
I'm sure there's quite a way to do this actually you only realize until you're halfway through
though and then you think well I'm halfway through a meso carry on
cool so I think we can just grab this into granular here is that possible
oh yes fantastic and what we can do with this is we can add some granular goodness to it
which is if you don't know or granular is get on youtube have a quick look it's almost like a
sample of it re-triggers
that's the same right
you're cool so
which is kind of cool
let's see what this sounds like
don't think it's the right tune
you can tell you can tell what kind of cool sounds you can make with that
cool so I just think that I think will work just like that cool so let's give a listen from the start
start till finish let's loop it a couple of times and let's say we can prove
and then what we're going to do is I think we're going to try and improve this build up
we've got the drop and then we can start building it out I think we need to add the arp
I want to bring the melody in somewhere again if I can so let's see how we can go with that
let's run from the start to finish though so just want to listen through it
like this good
oh yeah
okay something's glitching out there thanks Ableton just ruined the moment
what's going on I think I just accidentally deleted a section did I let me double check
the wonders of producing right so I'm going to retrieve this get this back again take a little
take a little break get some fresh air and then when I come back with you we're going to review
what we need to fix with this intro and then build out the rest of the tune